Ames Family Papers, 1812-2012
Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College
- SERIES III. INDIVIDUALS
  - GENERATION III
    - GENERATION IV
      - Ames, Blanche Ames (1879-1969)
        - Financial and legal materials
          - Management of family assets
            - Ames Textile Corporation and Ames Worsted Company: correspondence, memoranda, charts, and reports, 1935-54, undated (Box 60, Folder 5)
            - Heinze Electric Company
              - Correspondence, memoranda, and reports, 1915-37 (Box 60, Folder 6-7)
              - Annual reports and audits, 1918-32, undated (Box 60, Folder 8-10)
            - Ipswich Mills and Middlesex Company, 1919-32, undated (Box 60, Folder 10A)
            - Lowell Airport Corporation: contracts, correspondence, and reports, 1927-47 (Box 60, Folder 11)
            - National Lead Company and U.S. Cartridge: correspondence, 1918-26 (Box 61, Folder 1-2)
            - Silver Lake Company and Whittier Mills, 1919-31, undated (Box 61, Folder 3)
            - Wamesit Power Company
              - Correspondence, 1911-54 (Box 61, Folder 4-6)
              - Annual reports and statements, 1917-34 (Box 61, Folder 7-11)
        - Correspondence
          - Outgoing
            - Family
              - Ames, Adelbert (father), 1885-1929, undated (Box 62, Folder 1-7)
              - Ames, Adelbert and Blanche Butler Ames (parents), 1893-1937, undated (Box 62, Folder 8-9)
              - Ames, Adelbert, Jr. (son), 1922-61, undated (Box 62, Folder 10)
              - Ames, Amyas (son), 1915-66, undated (Box 62, Folder 11)
              - Ames, Anna (mother-in-law), 1915, undated (Box 62, Folder 12)
              - Ames, Blanche Butler (mother)
                - 1891-1939 (Box 62, Folder 13-21)
                - undated (Box 63, Folder 1-3)
              - Ames, Butler (brother), 1887-94, 1927 (Box 63, Folder 4)
              - Ames, Charley (cousin?), 1961 (Box 63, Folder 5)
              - Ames children, 1961, undated (Box 63, Folder 6)
              - Ames, Evelyn Perkins (daughter-in-law), 1954, undated (Box 63, Folder 7)
              - Ames, Oakes (husband), 1899-1905, undated (Box 63, Folder 8-9)
              - Ames, Oakes (grandson), 1955 (Box 63, Folder 10)
              - Ames, Oliver and Amyas (sons), 1915-54, undated (Box 63, Folder 11)
              - Borden, Ames (nephew), undated (Box 63, Folder 12)
              - Borden, Sarah Ames (sister), 1890-96, undated (Box 63, Folder 13)
              - Butler, Paul (uncle), 1895 (Box 63, Folder 14)
              - Davis, Evelyn Ames (daughter), 1940, 1958, undated (Box 63, Folder 15)
              - Davis, Evelyn Ames and Plimpton, Pauline Ames, undated (Box 63, Folder 16)
              - Hoblitzelle, Olivia Ames (granddaughter), undated (Box 63, Folder 16A)
              - Marshall, Andrew, Jr. (nephew) and Margaret Sayre, undated (Box 63, Folder 17)
              - Marshall, Jessie Ames (sister), 1902, 1956, undated (Box 63, Folder 18)
              - Pittarelli, Evelyn Davis (granddaughter), 1965 (Box 63, Folder 19)
              - Plimpton, Pauline Ames (daughter)
                - 1918-31 (Box 63, Folder 20-26)
                - 1932-65, undated (Box 63A, Folder 1-12)
              - Plimpton, Francis T.P. and Pauline, 1943, undated (Box 63A, Folder 13)
              - Plimpton, Francis T.P. (son-in-law), 1944 (Box 63A, Folder 14)
              - Stevens, Edith Ames (sister), 1895-1940, undated (Box 63A, Folder 15)
            - Others, 1898(?)-1967, undated (Box 64, Folder 1-2)
          - Incoming
            - Ames, Charlie and David Ames, 1951-61 (Box 64, Folder 3)
            - Plimpton, Fanny (Ann) Hastings and Ruth Plimpton, 1940s-60s (Box 64, Folder 4)
            - Children's education, health, and recreation, 1912-26, undated (Box 64, Folder 5-6)
            - Others
              - 1898-1924 (Box 64, Folder 7-13)
              - 1926-67, undated (Box 65, Folder 1-11)
          - Sax, Hally and Karl, 1944-67, undated (Box 65, Folder 12)
          - Orchids and the work of Oakes Ames (after his death)
            - Harvard University
              - Arnold Arboretum, 1950-66 (Box 66, Folder 1)
              - Botanical Museum and Oakes Ames Herbarium
                - Bierweiler, Louis, 1950-51, undated (Box 66, Folder 2)
                - Mangelsdorf, Paul, 1949-82 (Box 66, Folder 3)
                - Schultes, Richard, 1949-67, undated (Box 66, Folder 4)
                [see also Plimpton, Pauline Ames: Correspondence]
                - Schweinfurth, Charles, 1949-56, undated (Box 66, Folder 5)
            - Disposition of Oakes Ames' botanical library, 1956-88, undated (includes Pauline Ames Plimpton correspondence) (Box 66, Folder 6-7)
            - Donovan S. Correll re: Orchids of Guatemala, 1950-52, 1987 (Box 66, Folder 8)
            - Articles and correspondence about Oakes Ames and orchids, 1929-53 (Box 66, Folder 9)
        - Writings
          - Lectures and speeches
            - "Florida Orchids": typescript, 1947 (Box 66, Folder 10)
            - "Speaking on Orchids"
              - Typescript, 1951 (incomplete) (Box 66, Folder 11)
              - Draft manuscript, 1951 (Box 66, Folder 12)
            - "It Happened to Me": draft manuscript, 1954 (Box 66, Folder 13)
            - "Flora of the Islands of the Pacific": typescript, undated (Box 66, Folder 14)
          - Article: "Painting Round the World": The Woman's Journal, 30 Dec 1930 (Box 66, Folder 15)
          - Article: "Painting Round the World": The Woman's Journal, 30 Dec 1930 Travesty: Two College Men of Boston: Some Shakespearean Balderdash Depleted": typescript, 1938 (Box 66, Folder 16)
          - Poems, 1938-39, undated (Box 66, Folder 17)
          - Drafts and notes of other writings
            - "Title of Nobility": draft manuscript, 1934 (Box 66, Folder 18)
            - "Wanted: Normal Americans": typescript, 1943 (Box 66, Folder 19)
            - "Credo of Blanche Ames Ames": typescript, 1950s(?) (Box 66, Folder 20)
            - Unidentified, undated (Box 66, Folder 21)
          - Book: Adelbert Ames: Broken Oaths and Reconstruction in Mississippi, 1835-1933
            - Alleged factual errors in Profiles in Courage
              - Correspondence
                - John F. Kennedy: originals, copies, and photocopies, 1956 (Box 67, Folder 1-2)
                - Harper & Brothers Publishers, 1956 (Box 67, Folder 3)
                - Copies of correspondence and other documents, prepared by Blanche Ames Ames for use in potential lawsuit, circa 1963 (Box 67, Folder 4)
                - Saudek, Robert and Theodore Sorensen, 1963-64 (Box 67, Folder 5)
                - Others, 1956-60 (Box 67, Folder 6)
              - Articles and clippings, 1954-64, undated (Box 67, Folder 7)
            - Other correspondence
              - Publishers and editors, 1956-70, undated (Box 67, Folder 8-15)
              - General, 1951-66 (Box 68, Folder 1)
              - Attempts to find impartial biographer for Adelbert Ames, 1956 (Box 68, Folder 2)
            - Lists to whom book was sent, 1964 (Box 68, Folder 3)
            - Letters of thanks for copies of book, 1963-68, undated (Box 68, Folder 4-4A)
            - Publication announcement and reviews, 1964 (Box 68, Folder 5)
            - Typescript, undated (Box 68, Folder 6-9)
            - "Specimen pages," 1962 (Box 68, Folder 10)
            - Galley proof, circa 1962-63 (Box 69, Folder 1-3)
            - Galley proof: corrections and notes, undated (Box 69, Folder 4)
            - Corrections to text
              - Hunt, Draper 1960 (includes related correspondence) (Box 69, Folder 5)
              - Notes re: general corrections, undated (Box 69, Folder 6-7)
            - Drafts, undated (Box 69, Folder 8-9)
            - Drafts, undated (Box 70, Folder 1-6)
            - Illustrations and maps
              - Chapters 1-5 undated (Box 70, Folder 7-11)
              - Chapters 6-32 undated (Box 71, Folder 1-26)
              - Copies of reproduction photographs, undated (Box 72, Folder 1-2)
              - Photostats of maps, undated (Box 72, Folder 3)
            - Negatives, undated (Box 72, Folder 4)
            - Photographs not used, n.d (Box 72, Folder 5)
            - Notes about appendices, undated (Box 72, Folder 6-7)
            - Notes about maps and illustrations, n.d (Box 72, Folder 8-9)
            - Notes about bibliography, undated (Box 72, Folder 10)
            - Notes about possible revisions, undated (Box 72, Folder 11)
            - Research materials
              - Correspondence
                - Mississippi State Archives, 1951-58 (Box 73, Folder 1)
                - West Point Military Academy, 1957-58 (Box 73, Folder 2)
              - General requests for documents and for permission to publish, 1956-63, undated (Box 73, Folder 3)
              - Photostats of letters by Adelbert Ames 1895-1901 (from Mississippi State Archives) (Box 73, Folder 4)
              - Photostats of letters by Adelbert Ames 1862-1916, undated (from National Archives) (Box 73, Folder 5-6)
              - Notes about military career of Adelbert Ames, undated (Box 73, Folder 7)
              - "Annual Message of Adelbert Ames to the Legislature of Mississippi": pamphlet, 1876 (Box 73, Folder 8)
              - Fort Fisher (North Carolina)
                - "The Capture of Fort Fisher, North Carolina, January 15, 1865" by Adelbert Ames: pamphlet, 1865 (Box 73, Folder 9)
                - "The Capture of Fort Fisher, North Carolina, January 15, 1865" by Adelbert Ames: photocopy, n.d. (Box 73, Folder 10)
                - "Fort Fisher: Second Expedition" by Adelbert Ames: typescript, undated (Box 73, Folder 11)
                - "Account of the Capture of Fort Fisher" by H.C. Lockwood
                - Manuscript, circa 1865 (Box 73, Folder 12-13)
                - Typescript, undated (Box 74, Folder 1)
                - Brochures about Fort Fisher (and Fort Anderson), 1961-1962 (Box 74, Folder 2)
              - Brief biography of Ulysses S. Grant by Adelbert Ames: manuscript, undated (Box 74, Folder 3)
              - "My Story of Fredericksburg" by Joshua L. Chamberlain and "Comments by One Who Was There" by Ellis Spear: typescripts, undated (Box 74, Folder 4)
              - Ku Klux Klan: notes, undated (Box 74, Folder 5)
              - Lamar, Lucius Q.C. (Box 74)
              - Book: Lucius Q.C. Lamar: His Life, Timesand Speeches by Edward Mayes, 1896 (Box 74)
                - Notes, undated (Box 74, Folder 6)
              - Book: Adelbert Ames: Broken Oaths and Reconstruction in Mississippi, 1835-1933 (Box 74)
              - Mississippi
                - State constitution: notes, undated (Box 74, Folder 7)
                - Legal pamphlets, 1870-76 (Box 74, Folder 8)
              - Oaths: notes, undated (Box 74, Folder 9)
              - "Story of the Civil War": maps, undated (Box 74, Folder 10)
              - Notebook of clippings, 1898 (Box 75, Folder 1)
              - Photocopies of notebook of clippings (Box 75, Folder 2)
              - Article about U.S. Grant III: Boston Sunday Herald, 16 Oct 1960 (Box 75, Folder 3)
            - Notes
              - undated (Box 75, Folder 4-8)
              - undated (Box 76, Folder 1-8)
          - Book: Adelbert Ames, 1835-1933: General, Senator, Governor: The Story of His Life and Times...., published copy, 1964 (Box 77)
        - Activities
          - Emergency Fund Drive (for Boston charitable organizations): clippings, 1934 (Box 78, Folder 1)
          - Miscellaneous civic associations and organizations: correspondence, newsletters, pamphlets, and brochures, 1898-1966, undated (Box 78, Folder 2-4)
          - Art
            - General correspondence, 1913-63, undated (Box 78, Folder 5)
            - Boston studio: correspondence and leases, 1914-17 (Box 78, Folder 6)
            - Interior decoration commissions
              - Correspondence, notes, and sketches, 1930, undated (Box 78, Folder 7)
              - Paint samples, circa 1930 (Box 78, Folder 8)
            - Notebooks
              - 1911-12 (Box 78, Folder 9)
              - Circa 1918-54 (Box 79, Folder 1-7)
            - Notes, 1946, undated (Box 79, Folder 8)
            - Pencil sketches of Benjamin F. Butler, undated (Box 79, Folder 9)
            - Copies of portrait of Adelbert Ames as a Civil War general, 1933 (Box 79, Folder 10)
            - Paintings, photographs, prints, drawings, and sketches (various subjects), 1910-43, undated (Box 79, Folder 11)
            - Drawings and sketches of flowers, undated (Box 79, Folder 12)
            - Christmas cards, 1940-49, undated (Box 79, Folder 13)
            - Notes for color schemes in various paintings, 1915, undated (Box 79, Folder 14)
            - Reproduction photographs, slides, and negatives of paintings, undated (Box 80, Folder 1)
            - Color tint charts, undated (Box 80, Folder 2)
            - Color theory: "System of Color Standards"
              - Correspondence re: patent, 1922-26 (Box 80, Folder 3)
              - Essay, notes, and sketches, circa 1920 (Box 80, Folder 4)
              - Article: "Vision and the Technique of Art," by Adelbert Ames, Jr., C. A. Proctor and Blanche Ames Ames, Proceedings of the American Academy of Arts and Sciences, Feb 1923 (Box 80, Folder 5)
            - Art supplies: brochures and invoices, undated (Box 80, Folder 6)
            - Exhibits and art association memberships: correspondence, brochures, and pamphlets, 1923-62, undated (Box 80, Folder 7)
            - Art events: articles, brochures, and pamphlets, 1915-57, undated (Box 80, Folder 8)
            - Posthumous publications and exhibits about the art of Blanche Ames Ames
              - Orchids and Artists, 1991 (Box 80, Folder 9)
                [see also: Plimpton, Pauline Ames - Activities - Smith College]
              - Brockton Art Museum
                - General, 1982, undated (Box 80, Folder 10)
                - Clippings, 1982 (Box 80, Folder 11)
                - Correspondence, 1979-84, undated (Box 80, Folder 12)
                - Catalogue, and copies of photographs used in it, 1982 (Box 80, Folder 11)
              - Article: "There Were Ladies Present: American Women Cartoonists and Comic Artists in the Early Twentieth Century" by Alice Sheppard (Box 80, Folder 12)
            - Sketchbooks, 1899-1906, undated
              - Camera Lucida (used for botanical drawings), 1899-1906, undated (Box 81)
            - Inventions
              - Cutting lumber: correspondence and diagrams, 1938-40 (Box 82, Folder 1)
              - Excreta disposal system
                - Correspondence, photographs, and diagrams, 1966-67 (Box 82, Folder 2)
                - Notes and clippings, 1966-67 (Box 82, Folder 3)
                - Incineration information: correspondence and brochures, 1967 (Box 82, Folder 4)
                - U.S. patent application, 1967 (Box 82, Folder 5)
                - Information about existing sewage disposal patents, 1959-67 (Box 82, Folder 6)
              - Propeller snare: correspondence, invoices, clippings, diagrams, and photographs, 1940-82, undated (Box 82, Folder 7-10)
              - Snow fencing: correspondence and clipping, 1957 (Box 82, Folder 11)
              - Solar stills: correspondence, 1957 (Box 82, Folder 12)
              - Excreta disposal system: memorabilia (paraphernalia designed for possible use with this invention), circa 1967 (Box 83)
            - Reproductive rights and women's health
              - Birth control
                - Writings: review of book on contraceptive technique: draft, undated (Box 84, Folder 1)
                - American Birth Control League
                - Correspondence and invitations to meetings, 1922-34, undated (Box 84, Folder 2)
                - By-laws, minutes, and reports, 1931-35 (Box 84, Folder 3-5)
                - Articles, forms, and statistical information, 1929-34, undated (Box 84, Folder 6)
                - Brochures, clippings, and pamphlets, 1928, undated (Box 84, Folder 7)
                - Massachusetts Birth Control League
                - Correspondence
                - General
                - 1916-Jul 1919 (Box 84, Folder 8-10)
                - Aug 1919-65, undated (Box 85, Folder 1-6)
                - Marshall, Jessie Ames, 1928-38, undated (Box 85, Folder 7)
                - Legal, 1928-35, undated (Box 85, Folder 8)
                - Form letters, 1919-35 (Box 85, Folder 9)
                - Open letters, position papers, and speeches by BAA and others, 1928-35, undated (Box 85, Folder 10)
                - Drafts of letters and statements, and notes, 1925-35, undated (Box 86, Folder 1)
                - History of the organization: manuscripts, typescripts, and notes, 1921, undated (Box 86, Folder 2)
                - Constitution, 1916-32 (Box 86, Folder 3)
                - Annual meetings: minutes and reports, 1928-35 (Box 86, Folder 4)
                - Executive Board: membership lists, 1932-35 (Box 86, Folder 5)
                - Executive Committee: minutes, 1916-circa 1935 Financial materials (Box 86, Folder 6)
                - Treasurer's reports, 1931-34 (Box 86, Folder 7)
                - Fundraising
                - Correspondence and notes, circa 1916-20(?) (Box 86, Folder 8)
                - Forms, receipts, and lists of contributors, 1917-27 (Box 86, Folder 9)
                - Committees (various): minutes and reports, 1916-34, undated (Box 86, Folder 10)
                - Membership questionnaire, circa 1916(?) (Box 86, Folder 11)
                - Brochures, clippings, and pamphlets, 1935-36, undated (Box 86, Folder 12)
                - Doctors' Bill to Clarify the Law
                [see also Massachusetts Mothers' Health Council]
                - Correspondence, 1929-40, undated (Box 86, Folder 13-14)
                - Form letters, 1930-31, undated (Box 86, Folder 15)
                - List of invitees to lecture by Dr. James F. Cooper, May 1930 (Box 86, Folder 16)
                - Lists of Massachusetts Representatives and Senators, 1929-31 (Box 87, Folder 1)
                - Petitions, undated (Box 87, Folder 2)
                - Lists of supporters, undated (Box 87, Folder 3-4)
                - Lists of opponents, undated (Box 87, Folder 5)
                - Legislative leaflets and pamphlets, 1931 (Box 87, Folder 6)
                - Court case summaries, 1930-31 (Box 87, Folder 7)
                - Notes for reports and press releases, 1930-31, undated (Box 87, Folder 8)
                - Articles and clippings, 1931, undated (Box 87, Folder 9)
                - Parents' Petition to the Massachusetts Medical Society
                - Correspondence, 1929-35, undated (Box 87, Folder 10-11)
                - Speeches, 1929-30 (Box 87, Folder 12)
                - Articles and notes, 1925-34, undated (Box 88, Folder 1-4)
                - Petition forms, 1935 (Box 88, Folder 5)
                - Pamphlets, 1935 (Box 88, Folder 6)
                - Controversy re: ad in Boston Transcript 5 Jan 1935
                - Correspondence, notes, and reports, Dec 1934-Jan 1935 (Box 88, Folder 7)
                - Letters of resignation and reconsideration, Dec 1934-Jan 1935 (Box 88, Folder 8)
                - Clippings, Jan 1935 (Box 88, Folder 9)
                - Debate with the Catholic Church about birth control
                - Articles and editorials in Atlantic Monthly, 1939-40 (Box 88, Folder 10)
                - Correspondence, 1940 (Box 88, Folder 11)
                - Speeches by Blanche Ames Ames, 1940-41 (Box 88, Folder 12)
                - Essays by Blanche Ames Ames and Karl Sax, circa 1940 (Box 88, Folder 13)
                - Notes and fragments, undated (Box 88, Folder 14)
                - Pamphlets, 1931, 1938, undated (Box 88, Folder 15)
                - Clippings, 1929-35, undated (Box 88, Folder 16)
                - Mothers' Health Office
                - Correspondence, 1931-34, undated (Box 88, Folder 17)
                - Reports, 1931-34, undated (Box 88, Folder 18)
                - Massachusetts Mothers' Health Council: correspondence and essay, 1939-42, undated (Box 88, Folder 19)
                - Margaret Sanger
                - Visit by Blanche Ames Ames and Jessie Ames Marshall to Margaret Sanger: report and notes, Feb 1934 (Box 89, Folder 1)
                - "Margaret Sanger's Influence" by Blanche Ames Ames: typescript, undated (Box 89, Folder 2)
                - Article: "The Experts Debate the Birth Control Issue" by Margaret Sanger, Look, 8 Nov 1938 (Box 89, Folder 3)
                - American Civil Liberties Union and Sanger's right to hold a meeting: report, 1925 (Box 89, Folder 4)
                - Van Kleeck Allison case: clippings, 1916 (Box 89, Folder 5)
                - Other birth control organizations
                - Birth Control Federation of America: correspondence, 1940-41 (Box 89, Folder 6)
                - Family Welfare Foundation: correspondence, essays, and reports, 1919 (Box 89, Folder 7)
                - National Committee on Federal Legislation for Birth Control
                - Correspondence, 1928-35, undated (Box 89, Folder 8)
                - Newsletters and bulletins, 1929-35, undated (Box 89, Folder 9)
                - Planned Parenthood - World Population: correspondence, memoranda, and reports, 1965 (Box 89, Folder 10)
                - Population Association of America: reports, 1934 (Box 89, Folder 11)
                - Voluntary Parenthood League: correspondence and leaflets, 1915-30, undated (includes Mary Ware Dennett Defense Committee) (Box 89, Folder 12)
                - Published materials
                - Birth Control Review
                - Correspondence, 1916-34 (Box 89, Folder 13)
                - Published issues: May and Nov 1929, Mar 1931, Dec 1934, and Jan 1935 (Box 89, Folder 14)
                - Articles and newsletters, 1916-66, undated (Box 89, Folder 15-16)
                - Advertisements, 1918-66, undated (Box 89, Folder 17)
                - Clippings, 1916-66, undated (Box 89, Folder 18)
                - Eugenics
                - Brochures and pamphlets, 1931-32, undated (Box 90, Folder 1)
                - Eugenics: A Journal of Race Betterment, Jan & Feb 1931 (Box 90, Folder 2)
                - Medical Journal and Record, 21 Mar 1928 (Box 90, Folder 3)
                - New England Journal of Medicine, 1929-51 (Box 90, Folder 4-6)
              - New England Hospital
                - History, 1951, undated (Box 91, Folder 1)
                - By-laws and legal advice, undated (Box 91, Folder 2)
                - Staff by-laws, 1949-51 (Box 91, Folder 3)
                - Annual reports, 1887-1956 (incomplete run) (Box 91, Folder 4)
                - Annual reports of President and Administrator, 1953-54 (Box 91, Folder 5)
                - Board of Directors
                - Executive Committee: minutes, 1951-56, undated (Box 91, Folder 6)
                - Agendas, minutes, and reports, 1952-59 (Box 91, Folder 7)
                - Lists of members, 1951-58, undated (Box 91, Folder 8)
                - Policy re: men on NEH medical staff: memoranda, 1952 (Box 91, Folder 9)
                - Memoranda and notes, 1958, undated (Box 91, Folder 10)
                - Financial information: charts and reports, 1922-58 (Box 91, Folder 11)
                - Statistical information, 1946-55 (Box 91, Folder 12)
                - United Community Services: Faxon Report: reports, memoranda, and notes, 1950-54, undated (Box 91, Folder 13)
                - Evaluative reports and studies
                - "Report to the Trustees of the New England Hospital: A Study with Recommendations" by Philip D. Bonnet, 1952 (Box 91, Folder 14)
                - "A Study of the New England Hospital" by Charles F. Wilinsky, 1958 (Box 91, Folder 15)